Guide to the Records of the Leake and Watts Children's Home 1802-1983 (bulk 1831-1949) MS 377
New-York Historical Society
Leake and Watts Children's Home records
1802-1983 (bulk 1831-1949)
New-York Historical Society
Leake and Watts Children's Home, Inc.
MS 377
73.41 Linear feet 362 volumes, 34 boxes, 1 oversize folder
The collection contains records, 1831-1983 (bulk 1831-1949) of the Leake and Watts Children's Home (known originally as the Leake and Watts Orphan House and, since 2018, as Rising Ground) and records of two other child care agencies that merged into it: The Orphans' Home and Asylum of the Protestant Episcopal Church in New York (1851-1947), and the Sevilla-Hopewell Society (1947-1948). The Sevilla-Hopewell Society was a merger of The Sevilla Home for Children (1889-1947) with The Hopewell Society of Brooklyn (1921-1947), originally named The Society for the Aid of Friendless Women and Children (1869-1921). The collection contains records going back to the founding of each organization. The collection also contains unrelated records related to land in Masonville, New York, 1802-1865.
Scope and Content
The collection contains records, 1831-1983 (bulk 1831-1949) of the Leake and Watts Children's Home (known originally as the Leake and Watts Orphan House, and since 2018 as Rising Ground) and records of two other child care agencies that merged into it: The Orphans' Home and Asylum of the Protestant Episcopal Church in New York (1851-1947), and the Sevilla-Hopewell Society (1947-1948). The Sevilla-Hopewell Society was a merger of The Sevilla Home for Children (1889-1947) with The Hopewell Society of Brooklyn (1921-1947), originally named The Society for the Aid of Friendless Women and Children (1869-1921). The collection contains records going back to the founding of each organization.
Materials include, but are not limited to, minutes, annual and other reports, registers of admissions/discharges, financial records, correspondence, visitor's books, real estate records, scrapbooks, photographic prints and printing blocks, and bibles.
Also included (although not an integral part of above) are 10 volumes of rent, letter and account books, 1802-1865, relating to land in Masonville, Delaware County, New York originally owned by Rev. John Mason Knox, who also servced circa 1860's as Leake and Watts' treasurer.
Unusual materials include an 1843 "punishment book" recording the behavior of individual boys and discipline administered.
Related Material at the New-York Historical Society
Association for the Benefit of Colored Orphans Records, 1836-1972 (bulk 1850-1936)
Children's Aid Society Records, 1836-2006 (bulk 1853-1947)
New York Foundling Hospital Records, 1869-2009
Nursery and Child's Hospital Records 1854-1934
James H. Roosevelt Financial Records, 1784, 1820-1863, 1916. Includes two volumes, and a portion of another, of the records maintained by Roosevelt and Cornelius Bogert as trustees for the Leake & Watts Orphan House and estate of Augustine H. Lawrence, 1843-46.
Graham Windham Records, 1806-2011
Watts Papers, 1689-1870 (bulk 1740-1840)
John Watts De Peyster Papers, 1849-1857
Historical Note
The Leake and Watts Orphan House/Leake and Watts Children's Home
The Leake and Watts Orphan House was founded in 1831 by John Watts, Jr., according to the will and bequest of John George Leake. Motivated by a sense of social responsibility, Leake (1752-1827), a prominent New York lawyer, and Watts (1749-1836), three term Speaker of the N.Y. Assembly and two term Congressman, envisioned a private non-sectarian charitable organization for children in need. The Rector of Trinity Church was president of the Board of Trustees. Board members included ministers of the Dutch Collegiate and First Presbyterian Churches, and the Mayor of New York City.
In 1843, the Leake and Watts Orphan House opened at 112th Street and Amsterdam Avenue in a significant Greek Revival building designed by Ithiel Town which still stands on the grounds of the current Cathedral of St. John the Divine. At its opening it housed 60 boys, and soon expanded to include girls as well. Continuing to extend its capacity and services, it moved in 1891 to its current location in Yonkers N.Y., a 30-acre farm formerly owned by thespian Edward Forest with grounds designed by Frederick Law Olmstead. In 1905, General John Watts de Peyster, a long-term benefactor, bequeathed additional land in Tivoli N.Y. Edwin Gould provided financial support to develop the property.
In 1921, Leake & Watts introduced to their Yonkers campus a "cottage system" of smaller group residences. In 1924 they began calling the Yonkers facility the Leake and Watts Home School. The Tivoli facility became the Leake and Watts Farm School; it provided both vocational farm training and a summer camp. In the early 1930s Leake and Watts expanded its mission; in addition to orphans, it served dependent children from broken homes. A Social Service Department established in 1937 addressed children's therapeutic needs. In 1944, a new Foster Home Department placed children in community foster homes. The Tivoli land was sold in 1945.
In 1947, the organization changed its name to The Leake and Watts Children's Home, Inc. The same year, it merged with the Orphan Home and Asylum of the Protestant Episcopal Church in New York. In 1949 Leake and Watts merged with the Sevilla-Hopewell Society, a child care agency which was itself a recent merger of the Hopewell Society of Brooklyn (1921-1947) with the Sevilla Home for Children (New York 1889-1947).
The bulk of the archival records of Leake and Watts at the New-York Historical Society end at 1949. However, the organization continued to develop. The name changed to Leake and Watts Services, Inc. in the 1990's and to Rising Ground in April 2018. Rising Ground/Leake and Watts provides preventative, educational, early childhood, foster care, housing, physical and mental health, and juvenile justice services, to around 3,000 abused and neglected children, children with special needs, teen parents, parents struggling with substance abuse or other issues, young adults with developmental disabilities learning to live independently, and others in need. For more information on current services, visit the organization's website at https://www.risingground.org/.
The Orphans Home and Asylum of the Protestant Episcopal Church in New York
The Orphans Home and Asylum of the Protestant Episcopal Church in New York was founded in 1851 and incorporated in 1854. It was initiated by a member of the church (possibly Mrs. J.H. Hobart who served as the first Directress) along with Rev. J.H. Hobart (first Secretary)and Rev. Dr. Wainwright (Chairman), in order that there might be a place for orphaned children who had been baptized in the faith. As it expanded, it moved quickly from one room on Robinson Street, to larger quarters on Renwick Street, to Hammond Street, to 146-148 West 39th Street, and then circa 1861 to a home built to the asylum's specifications on 49th Street and Lexington Avenue. In 1903 the New York Central Railroad bought the property, obliging the asylum to move to a new building on Convent Avenue between 135-137th Streets in 1905. It merged with Leake and Watts in 1947.
The Society for the Aid of Friendless Women and Children/Hopewell Society of Brooklyn
The Society for the Aid of Friendless Women and Children was founded in 1869 as a non-sectarian organization with a board of managers representing many churches in Brooklyn. Located at 20 Concord Street, it offered temporary shelter for women in crisis, and temporary or long-term shelter for children. Girls were accepted up to the age of 16. Boys were accepted up to the age of 6. Children who lived at the home attended local schools, and beginning in 1901 girls were also trained in housework to enable them to find work as domestics. A donation by Edwin Gould enabled the Society to open a summer facility for the children, the Summerland Home in Demarest New Jersey. In 1921, the Board of Managers voted to shorten and simplify the name of the organization, exchanging it for a name with the same spirit. The Society for the Aid of Friendless Women and Children became the Hopewell Society, with the same board and the same services. In 1922 the Concord Street property was sold. The organization moved to 218 Gates Avenue in Brooklyn. Additional annexes, one for adolescent girls and one for elderly women, were opened on Monroe Street nearby. In 1928 the Summerland property in Demarest was sold, and a new Summerland camp in New City, NY, was opened. The women's shelter was discontinued in 1942, but the home for children continued. In 1947, The Hopewell Society of Brooklyn merged with the Sevilla Home for Children, to become the Sevilla-Hopewell Society. The combined entity was incorporated into the Leake and Watts Children's Home in 1949.
The Sevilla Home for Children
The Sevilla Home for Children was named for Jose Sevilla, a Peruvian who made his fortune in New York. Upon his death in 1886, his will provided the means to establish the institution, and stipulated its form and rules. It was incorporated in 1889. In 1908, after several years during which the board untangled legal issues, found a location and built a facility, the institution opened its doors on Lafayette Avenue between Manida and Barretto Streets in the Hunts Point section of the Bronx. The non-sectarian institution accepted mentally and physically healthy yet destitute girls (usually either orphans or half-orphans) between the ages of five and ten, who were surrendered by their guardian. The girls stayed at the home until the age of 16, at which point they returned to a guardian or employment. Girls who created problems were removed from the home earlier, and returned to a guardian. The home generally housed around 60 girls at a time, although there were years with more and fewer girls. In 1945 the institution became racially integrated and began taking referrals from the city. In 1947, it merged with the Hopewell Society to become the Sevilla-Hopewell Society, using Sevilla's property in the Bronx and Hopewell's Summerland Camp in New City, NY. In 1949 the new organization was incorporated into the Leake and Watts Children's Home.
Access Restrictions
Records less than 70 years old are restricted, except to researchers with written permission from Rising Ground (the current organizational name of Leake and Watts). Records older than 70 years old are open for scholarly research.
Researchers who wish to view open materials will register as Manuscript users, and be allowed access to the unrestricted materials in the collection.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The collection was donated in 1983, by The Leake and Watts Children's Home, Inc.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in seven series, according to the organization that created the records. Series I contains records of the Leake and Watts Orphan House/Leake and Watts Children's Home Inc. Series II-V contain records of the other child care agencies that merged into it in 1947. Series VI and VII contain unrelated and miscellaneous records.
Missing Title
Series I - Leake and Watts Orphan House in the City of New York/Leake and Watts Children's Home Inc., 1831-1971
Series II - Orphans' Home and Asylum of the Protestant Episcopal Church of New York, 1851-1949
Series III - Society for the Aid of Friendless Women and Children 1869-1921/Hopewell Society of Brooklyn, 1921-1947
Series IV - Sevilla Home for Children, 1889-1947
Series V - Sevilla-Hopewell Society, 1948-1949
Series VI - Masonville (N.Y.), 1802-1865
Series VII - Bibles, Constitution of the Colored Orphan Asylum, volume from unidentified agency
Agricultural education -- United States.; Camps -- United States -- History.; Charities -- New York (State) -- New York.; Foster children -- United States -- History.; Orphanages -- New York (State) -- New York.; Orphans -- New York (State) -- New York.; Social service -- New York (State) -- New York.; Social work administration -- New York (State) -- New York.; Social work with children -- New York (State) -- New York -- History.; Social work with youth -- New York (State) -- New York -- History.; Vocational education -- United States.; Women's shelters -- New York (State) -- New York.; Bronx (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Delaware County (N.Y.); Demarest (N.J.); Masonville (N.Y.); New York (N.Y.); Yonkers (N.Y.); Account books.; Annual reports.; Blueprints (reprographic copies); Deeds.; Financial records.; Ledgers (account books); Letters (correspondence); Minutes (administrative records); Pamphlets.; Photographic prints.; Programs (documents).; Printing blocks; Receipts (financial records); Registers (lists); Reports.; Visitors' books; Gould, Edwin, 1866-1933; Knox, John Mason; Leake, John George, 1752-1827; Mason, John M. (John Mitchell), 1770-1829; Watts, John, 1749-1836; Hopewell Society of Brooklyn; Leake and Watts' Orphan House; Leake & Watts Services; Orphans' Home and Asylum of the Protestant Episcopal Church in New York; Sevilla-Hopewell Society; Sevilla Home for Children; Society for the Aid of Friendless Women and Children (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Summerland Home
- Series I - Leake and Watts Orphan House in the City of New York/Leake and Watts Children's Home, Inc., 1831-1983 (bulk 1831-1949)
  Arrangement
  The series contains records of the Leake and Watts Orphan House/Leake and Watts Children's Home, arranged in ten subseries, as follows:
  Subseries I.1 - Minutes, 1831-1949
  Subseries I.2 - Reports, 1844-1949
  Subseries I.3 - Administrative Records, 1816-1949
  Subseries I.4 - Numbered Files from the Office of William A. Kirk,circa 1918-1965
  Subseries I.5 - Financial Records, 1833-1957
  Subseries I.6 - Records of Children, Clubs and Activities
  Subseries I.7 - Real Estate Records
  Subseries I.8 - Printed Materials
  Subseries I.9 - Visual Materials
  Subseries I.10 - Clippings
  Missing Title
  Subseries I.4 - Numbered Files from the Office of William A. Kirk, circa 1918-1965
  Subseries I.6 - Records of Children, Clubs, Activities and Alumni, 1843-1964
  Subseries I.7 - Real Estate Records, circa 1822-1960
  Subseries I.8 - Printed Materials, circa 1843-1964
  Subseries I.9 - Visual Materials, circa 1910-1983
  Subseries I.10 - Clippings, circa 1857-1980
  - Subseries I.1 - Minutes, 1831-1949
    Scope and Content
    The series contains Minutes of the Board of Trustees 1831-1949 (35 volumes and 11 folders), followed by Minutes of the House Committee 1850-1914 (6 volumes). Minutes of the Leake & Watts Association, an alumni organization, may be found in Series I.6 - Records of Children, Clubs and Activities.
    - Minutes - Board of Trustees, 1831-1849 (Offsite-box LW-1, Volume 1)
    - Minutes - Board of Trustees, 1849-1875 (Offsite-box LW-1, Volume 2)
    - Minutes - Board of Trustees, 1875-1895 (Offsite-box LW-1, Volume 3)
    - Minutes - Board of Trustees, 1895-1905 (Offsite-box LW-1, Volume 4)
    - Minutes - Board of Trustees, 1906-1916 (Offsite-box LW-1, Volume 5)
    - Minutes - Board of Trustees, 1916-1918 (Offsite-box LW-2, Volume 6)
    - Minutes - Board of Trustees, 1918-1920 (Offsite-box LW-2, Volume 7)
    - Minutes - Board of Trustees, 1921-1922 (Offsite-box LW-2, Volume 8)
    - Minutes - Board of Trustees, 1923 (Offsite-box LW-2, Volume 9)
    - Minutes - Board of Trustees, 1924 (Offsite-box LW-3, Volume 10)
    - Minutes - Board of Trustees, 1925 (Offsite-box LW-3, Volume 11)
    - Minutes - Board of Trustees, 1926 (Offsite-box LW-3, Volume 12)
    - Minutes - Board of Trustees, 1927 (Offsite-box LW-3, Volume 13)
    - Minutes - Board of Trustees, 1928 (Offsite-box LW-4, Volume 14)
    - Minutes - Board of Trustees, 1929 (Offsite-box LW-4, Volume 15)
    - Minutes - Board of Trustees, 1930 January-September (Offsite-box LW-4, Volume 16)
    - Minutes - Board of Trustees, 1930 September - 1931 January (Offsite-box LW-4, Volume 17)
    - Minutes - Board of Trustees, 1931 January - May (Offsite-box LW-5, Volume 18)
    - Minutes - Board of Trustees, 1931 May - 1932 April (Offsite-box LW-5, Volume 19)
    - Minutes - Board of Trustees, 1932-1933 (Offsite-box LW-5, Volume 20)
    - Minutes - Board of Trustees, 1934-1935 (Offsite-box LW-5, Volume 21)
    - Minutes - Board of Trustees, 1936 (Offsite-box LW-6, Volume 22)
    - Minutes - Board of Trustees, 1936 November - 1937 December (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
    - Minutes - Board of Trustees, 1938 (Offsite-box LW-6, Volume 23)
    - Minutes - Board of Trustees, 1938 January - December (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
    - Minutes - Board of Trustees, 1939 (Offsite-box LW-6, Volume 24)
    - Minutes - Board of Trustees, 1940 (Offsite-box LW-6, Volume 25)
    - Minutes - Board of Trustees, 1940 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
    - Minutes - Board of Trustees, 1940-1941 (Offsite-box LW-7, Volume 26)
    - Minutes - Board of Trustees, 1941 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4)
    - Minutes - Board of Trustees, 1941-1942 (Offsite-box LW-7, Volume 27)
    - Minutes - Board of Trustees, 1942 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5)
    - Minutes - Board of Trustees, 1942-1943 (Offsite-box LW-7, Volume 28)
    - Minutes - Board of Trustees, 1943 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6)
    - Minutes - Board of Trustees, 1943-1944 (Offsite-box LW-7, Volume 29)
    - Minutes - Board of Trustees, 1944 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 7)
    - Minutes - Board of Trustees, 1944-1945 (Offsite-box LW-7, Volume 30)
    - Minutes - Board of Trustees, 1945 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 8)
    - Minutes - Board of Trustees, 1945-1946 (Offsite-box LW-8, Volume 31)
    - Minutes - Board of Trustees, 1946 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 9)
    - Minutes - Board of Trustees, 1946-1947 (Offsite-box LW-8, Volume 32)
    - Minutes - Board of Trustees, 1947 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 10)
    - Minutes - Board of Trustees, 1947 May - December (Offsite-box LW-8, Volume 33)
    - Minutes - Board of Trustees, 1948 (Offsite-box LW-8, Volume 34)
    - Minutes - Board of Trustees, 1948 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 11)
    - Minutes - Board of Trustees, 1948 October - 1949 February (Offsite-box LW-8, Volume 35)
    - Minutes - House Committee, 1843-1850 (Offsite-box LW-8, Volume 36)
    - Minutes - House Committee, 1850-1854 (Offsite-box LW-8, Volume 37)
    - Minutes - House Committee, 1854-1860 (Offsite-box LW-8, Volume 38)
    - Minutes - House Committee, 1861-1868 (Offsite-box LW-8, Volume 39)
    - Minutes - House Committee, 1869-1880 (Offsite-box LW-8, Volume 40)
    - Minutes - House Committee, 1881-1914 (Offsite-box LW-9, Volume 41)
  - Subseries I.2 - Reports, 1844-1949
    The series consists of two volumes and about 4 boxes of reports, arranged in the following order:
    I.2A - Annual Reports, 1916-1949
    I.2B - Treasurer's Reports to the Board of Trustees, 1851-1914
    I.2C - Auditor's Reports to the Board of Trustees, 1912-1949
    I.2D - Superintendent's Reports to the Board of Trustees, 1844-1935
    I.2E - Monthly Reports to NYC Department of Public Welfare, 1941-1947
    I.2F - School Reports, 1844-1913
    The collection of annual reports is incomplete. Most reports from the 1930's and 1940s are missing.
    - Subseries I.2A - Annual Reports, 1916-1949
      - Annual Report, 1916 July (Offsite-box 1, Folder 12)
      - Unbound Annual Report Variation - "Leake Booklet", 1916 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 13)
      - Annual Report, 1917-1918 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 14)
      - Annual Report, 1918 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 15)
      - Annual Report, 1919 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 16)
      - Annual Report, 1920 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 17)
      - Annual Report, 1921 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 18)
      - Annual Report, 1922 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 19)
      - Annual Report, 1923 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 20)
      - Annual Report, 1924 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 21)
      - Annual Report - Home School, 1925 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 22)
      - Annual Report, 1928 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 23)
      - Annual Report, 1929-1930 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 24)
      - Annual Report - Leake and Watts School, 1945 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 25)
      - Annual Report, 1949 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 26)
    - Subseries I.2B - Treasurer's Annual Reports to the Board of Trustees, 1851-1914
      - Treasurer's Reports to the Board of Trustees, 1851-1861, 1864, 1866 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 1)
      - Treasurer's Annual Reports to the Board of Trustees, 1873-1890 (Offsite-box LW-9, Volume 42)
      - Treasurer's Annual Reports to the Board of Trustees, 1904-1914 (Offsite-box LW-9, Volume 43)
    - Subseries I.2C - Auditor's Reports to the Board of Trustees, 1912-1949
      - Auditor's Report 1912, with Summary of Accounts 1833-1912 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 2)
      - Auditor's Reports, 1915, 1924 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 3)
      - Auditor's Reports, 1938-1939, 1942-1944, 1946 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 4)
      - Auditor's Reports, 1947-1949 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 5)
    - Subseries I.2D - Superintendent's Reports to the Board of Trustees, 1844-1935
      - Superintendent's Annual Reports to the Board of Trustees, 1844-1858 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 6)
      - Superintendent's Annual Reports to the Board of Trustees, 1859-1869 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 7)
      - Superintendent's Annual Reports to the Board of Trustees, 1870-1877 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 1)
      - Superintendent's Annual Reports to the Board of Trustees, 1878-1890 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 2)
      - Superintendent's Quarterly and Annual Reports to the Board of Trustees, 1907-1914 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 3)
      - Superintendent's Quarterly and Monthly Reports to the Board of Trustees, 1915-1916 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 4)
      - Superintendent's Monthly Reports to the Board of Trustees, 1917-1920 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 5)
      - Superintendent's Monthly Reports to the Board of Trustees, 1921-1927 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 6)
      - Superintendent's Weekly Reports to the Board of Trustees, 1928 November 16 - 1929 May 31 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 1)
      - Superintendent's Weekly Reports to the Board of Trustees, 1929 June 14 - 1929 December 27 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 2)
      - Superintendent's Weekly Reports to the Board of Trustees, 1930 January 3 - May 29 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 3)
      - Superintendent's Weekly Reports to the Board of Trustees, 1930 June 6 - December 26 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 4)
      - Superintendent's Weekly and Monthly Reports to the Board of Trustees, 1931 January 2 - December 4 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 5)
      - Superintendent's Monthly Reports to the Board of Trustees, 1932 January 8 - 1933 December 8 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 6)
      - Superintendent's Monthly Reports to the Board of Trustees, 1934 January 10 - 1935 December 17 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 1)
    - Subseries I.2E - Monthly Reports to the N.Y.C. Department of Welfare, 1941-1947
      - Monthly Reports to the N.Y.C. Department of Public Welfare, 1941 January - 1942 March (Offsite-box 5, Folder 2)
      - Monthly Reports to the N.Y.C. Department of Welfare, 1942 April - 1945 April (Offsite-box 5, Folder 3)
      - Monthly Reports to the N.Y.C. Department of Welfare, 1945 June - 1947 December (Offsite-box 5, Folder 4)
    - Subseries I.2F - School Reports, 1844-1913
      - School Reports, 1844-1913 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 5)
  - Subseries I.3 - Administrative Records, 1816-1961
    The subseries contains administrative correspondence, memoranda, and legal documents arranged chronologically. Much of the correspondence is addressed to (or sometimes composed by) the Treasurer, the Board of Trustees, or the Superintendent. The subseries includes by-laws from 1857, 1883 and 1911. The final four folders in the subseries, housed in Box 8, include material separated by subject -- one folder on cemeteries, three folders related to the administration of the school.
    Additional administrative correspondence and legal documents may be found in Subseries I.4 - Numbered Files from the Office of William A. Kirk.